<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's second warning-piece, or, Observations on the barbarous attempt to murther Justice Arnold, April the 15th 1680 containing 1. a true relation of the matter of fact, 2. some remarks on the circumstances, 3. a true copy of the pretended speech of Evans the popish priest, executed in Glamorganshire, as it was lately printed by the papists, in revenge of whose prosecution, this assassination is presumed to have been committed : with a comment on the hypocritical speech of that dying traytor.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13304375</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13304375</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98961</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's second warning-piece, or, Observations on the barbarous attempt to murther Justice Arnold, April the 15th 1680 containing 1. a true relation of the matter of fact, 2. some remarks on the circumstances, 3. a true copy of the pretended speech of Evans the popish priest, executed in Glamorganshire, as it was lately printed by the papists, in revenge of whose prosecution, this assassination is presumed to have been committed : with a comment on the hypocritical speech of that dying traytor.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arnold, John, --  Justice.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:98961:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S Second Warning-piece; OR OBSERVATIONS ON THE Barbarous Attempt to <hi>Murther</hi> Juſtice <hi>ARNOLD April</hi> the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1680.</head>
            <p>CONTAINING
<list>
                  <item>1. A True Relation of the Matter of Fact.</item>
                  <item>2. Some <hi>Remarks</hi> on the Circumſtances.</item>
                  <item>3. A true Copy of the pretended Speech of <hi>Evans</hi> the <hi>Popiſh Prieſt,</hi> executed in <hi>Glamorganſhire</hi> (as it was lately printed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) in <hi>Revenge</hi> of whoſe <hi>Proſecution,</hi> this <hi>Aſſaſſination</hi> is preſumed to have been committed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With a <hi>Comment</hi> on the Hypocritical Speech of that dying <hi>TRAYTOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFTER the horrid bloody <hi>Plot</hi> of the Papiſts, <hi>diſcovered</hi> even as by Miracle, prov'd by <hi>various</hi> yet fully concurrent and ſatisfactory Evidence, <hi>confirm</hi>'d by undeniable Circumſtances, as <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Murther, <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters <hi>&amp;c. decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> by his Majeſty in repeated Proclamations, by ſeveral Parliaments, in rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated unanimous Votes, <hi>manifeſted</hi> by Legal Convictions of many of the Traitors, <hi>Flight</hi> of divers others, and ſubtle Evaſions uſed by that Party to <hi>ſhufftle off</hi> many more of the moſt conſiderable Conſpirators from Juſtice, it could ſcarce be imagined (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> being moſt happily on the ſame ſide) that theſe <hi>Cockatrices Eggs</hi> ſhould not have been throughly <hi>cruſht,</hi> when their <hi>Neſt</hi> was ſo plainly diſcovered; that their traiterous <hi>Malice</hi> ſhould not have been perfectly diſarm'd, theſe <hi>Foxes</hi> muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel'd, as well as unkennel'd, theſe <hi>Bulls</hi> of <hi>Baſhan</hi> hamſtrung; that their <hi>Religion</hi> (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me that in Cuſtom I apply that <hi>Sacred Name</hi> to ſuch a Chaos of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and Atheiſtical <hi>Villany</hi>) ſhould not long e're this, have been <hi>abominated</hi> by every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, every true <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> every real <hi>Servant</hi> of God, every <hi>honeſt Subject</hi> to his King.</p>
            <p>But ſo it unhappily has <hi>happen'd,</hi> after all theſe <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> theſe ſelf-evident Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, ſuch is the <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Diligence,</hi> the impudence and Artifice of the Popiſh and <hi>Be-Jeſuited</hi> Party, and ſuch the Eaſineſs, Incredulity or Treachery of ſome that call themſelves Proteſtants, that ſtill theſe curſed Machinations ('tis juſtly fear'd) go on, and thrive, and gather Strength and Encouragement, they have out-brazen'd their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Guilt, turn'd the dreadful Conſpiracy into a matter of <hi>Ridicule</hi> and Merriment, when in vain they had attempted to debauch, corrupt the Kings Evidence (as by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Inſtances was irrefragably prov'd to the Satisfaction of all the World) they next with <hi>Libels</hi> and <hi>Lampoons,</hi> with forged Stories, and impudent printed Slanders, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to repreſent them as <hi>Rogues,</hi> whom with all their <hi>Bribes</hi> and their Baits, they could not make ſuch, and to render them contemptible and unworthy of Credit, and herein All the <hi>Drolls,</hi> and the <hi>Witts with wry-mouths,</hi> the <hi>Bullies</hi> and the <hi>Hectors,</hi> the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98961:2"/>
               <hi>Tories</hi> and the <hi>Simpletons,</hi> in a word, all the <hi>Riff-raff</hi> of the Town, the <hi>Burthen</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> and the <hi>Scandal</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> moſt readily have joyn'd.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially (as their laſt Refuge) they have made it their Buſineſs to fling the Odium upon other people, to embroil Proteſtants with mutual Fears, Miſunderſtandings and Jealouſies, and though even in <hi>this too,</hi> indulgent Heaven has moſt ſignally in ſeveral Inſtances detected their Deſign, yet ſo far have the Powers of <hi>Hell,</hi> and Charms of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical Imps</hi> prevail'd, that not a few weak inconſiderate, though otherwiſe perhaps well-meaning Proteſtants have been inveigled into too good an Opinion of theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners, and too hard Thoughts and unjuſt Suſpitions of their Innocent, Loyal, and peaceable Neighbours. This miſchievous work, has of late been chiefly carried on under-ground in Masks, and borrowed Faces, of the many thouſands about this City very lately known to be moſt furious deſperate Papiſts, there is now ſcarce one (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) that will own himſelf a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> No, No, Oaths, Sacraments, nay railing againſt his Holineſs, provided it be with a <hi>God-dam-me,</hi> and to carry on the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh <hi>Health;</hi> all ſhall be ſwallow'd and permitted by large Diſpenſations, ſo as ſtill it may help forward the grand Cauſe, and neatly ſet Proteſtants together by the Ears.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, theſe new <hi>Diſguis'd Sons</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (whoſe Ruin in truth they principally deſign) palliate Popiſh Treaſons and Murthers, and <hi>Create</hi> firſt, and then Exaggerate imaginary Fears and Dangers from <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diſſenters; But tell us, you pragmatick <hi>Make-bates,</hi> you <hi>Pope-and-Fanatick</hi> Villains, you <hi>Citt-and-Bumpkin</hi> Incendiaries, tell us, if you can, that one <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> that one <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> who ſince his Majeſties Glorious, Happy, and Gracious Reſtauration (except long ſince a wild <hi>Small-coal-man,</hi> and a handful of <hi>Venner</hi>'s <hi>mad crue,</hi> with whom all other Nonconformiſts were ſo far from joyning, that both then, and ever ſince, they deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch Rebellious Frenzie) what one Diſſenter, I ſay, beſides, throughout the whole Nation, in now <hi>Twenty</hi> years peaceable Government, hath acted or preached any thing Trayterous or Rebllious? If you know any ſuch, proſecute them; but till you are able to do that on better Evidence than your Meal-tub Knights of the Poſt, or <hi>Squire Crack-fart</hi>'s ſilly <hi>Pictures,</hi> and more ſilly <hi>Pamphlets.</hi> Is it not plain to any that wears Common Senſe about him, that all this is nothing but <hi>Romiſh Duſt</hi> and <hi>Smoak</hi> that they would <hi>blow</hi> into our <hi>Eyes?</hi> ſo to ſet us a quarrelling blind-fold amongſt our ſelves, that you might more conveniently knock out all our Brains? And then ſhould the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> (to you the moſt <hi>odious,</hi> as being undoubtedly the moſt <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> in the Reformed World) have been voted as Fanatical and Heretical as any of thoſe whom you now ſo loudly declaim againſt.</p>
            <p>The honeſt Reader will excuſe this long (not impertinent) Preamble. Now to the Matter.</p>
            <p>At this deplorable Juncture, when the Plot lay <hi>half-buried</hi> in new-rais'd Duſt, when the King's Witneſſes were publickly (though not allowedly) ſcorn'd and libell'd; when <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Tragedy was made Matter of Romance, when Gentlemen moſt active to ſerve (nay to ſave) their King, their Religion, and the Liberties and Properties of their Countrey, were repreſented as the moſt odious and dangerous. In this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy God has been pleaſed once again to awaken the Nation, by Infatuating and Diſplaying theſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> in another of their moſt nefarious Attempts: the true Relation whereof (according to our beſt Information) follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>JOHN ARNOLD</hi> Eſquire, a Perſon (as 'tis ſaid) of above fifteen hundred pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> and a very worthy Gentleman, being formerly, before the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the preſent damnable <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and being then active, according to his Oath and Duty, to give information of, and proſecute growing Papiſts in that County. He was (as 'tis ſaid, by certain miſrepreſentations) put out of the Commiſſion a little before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of that Conſpiracy; whereupon coming to <hi>London,</hi> he was deſirous to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his <hi>Offence</hi> that might occaſion ſuch his Removal: and upon Enquiry was told, That <hi>Edward Coleman</hi> (then an Eminent Servant to ſome of the Family of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and ſince juſtly hang'd for Treaſon to murther the King <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) had offered ſomething to his prejudice; (<hi>Innocence</hi> is alwayes the Nurſe of Reſolution) therefore Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> then repaired to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Coleman's</hi> Dwelling-houſe, deſiring to ſpeak with his <hi>High-and-mighty-ſhip,</hi> and know what he had to charge him with, offering to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98961:2"/>appear to anſwer for any Miſdemeanour before King and Council, or any lawful Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature. But at that time, that mighty Traytor, buoy'd up with extraordinary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, and full of Damnable Buſineſs, was too Great (forſooth) to be ſpoken with, and all the ſatisfaction he could get was, <hi>That he was not at leiſure to anſwer ſuch a Fellow as he was.</hi> Which Inſolence to a Gentleman of his worth, it may well be thought, could not but move him to ſome Paſſion, and, amongſt other <hi>Repartees,</hi> he parted with theſe words, (fatally prophetick to <hi>Coleman</hi>) <hi>Sirrah, I ſhall live to ſee you hanged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Accident being already related in Print, we took leave here to repeat it, to ſhew that this Gentleman has long lain under the evil Eye of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> whoſe Plot being ſoon after diſcovered, His Majeſty was pleaſed again to put Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> into Commiſſion, who vigorouſly diſcharg'd his Duty in ſeveral remarkable Services, as the Diſcovery of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Colledge, Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at <hi>Combe</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> which he, by Order of the Council, cauſed to be burn'd; the ſeizing and proſecuting that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Raſcal Father <hi>Lewis</hi> the Jeſuit, (that cheated a poor Maid of a conſiderable Sum of money to pray her Father's Soul out of Purgatory.) By theſe and the like faithful Services, he had contracted upon himſelf the further Malice of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who frequently threatned to aſſaſſinate him; particularly one <hi>Evans</hi> a Jeſuit, gave out that he would <hi>Piſtol</hi> him, but that bloody <hi>Ruffian-prieſt</hi> was prevented, by being hang'd ſoon after for Treaſon, at <hi>Cardiff</hi> in <hi>Glamorgan</hi> Shire. However, their implacable Spleen ſtill reviv'd and grew more furious, only waiting an Opportunity, which now they thought they had obtained; for ſome Difference happening between Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi> another Juſtice of Peace, who 'tis ſaid had been an Encourager inſtead of a Suppreſſer of Papiſts, Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> for his ill Practices accuſed him to the King and Council, and ſo came to <hi>London</hi> with ſeveral Witneſſes to make good the Charge. The Matter being to be hear'd at the Board on Friday the 16th. of this Inſtant <hi>April,</hi> the ſaid Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> was over-night (<hi>viz. Thurſday</hi> the 15th.) with ſome Perſons of Quality at the <hi>Apollo</hi> (commonly called the <hi>Divel</hi>) Tavern near Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Bar, but being very mindful of his Buſineſs, about ten a Clock took an Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſlip from his Company, deſiging to ſtep to his Council, Mr. <hi>Phillips,</hi> at his Houſe in little <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> Fields, and ſo return to them. As he went forth he call'd to his Servants (for he had two men that attended him) to follow him, but he going out ſo haſtily and privately without the Company's breaking up, they did not hear not perceive him, but in their Stead, certain Bloody Aſſaſſinates (who 'tis thought had long dogg'd him up and down, as their Brethren did Juſtice <hi>Godfrey</hi>) follow'd him at the Heels (he thinking they had been his own men) up <hi>Bell-yard</hi> to the end of <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-apos</hi> Lane, which ſuppoſing to be a fit place for their barbarous Deſigns, they there fell upon him, being three in number, one firſt with a Cudgel, ſtriking him with all his Force behind on the Calves of the Leggs, which making him ſtagger, another at the ſame Inſtant flung a Cloak over his Head, and ſo muffled him, that he might not cry out, they then having thrown him down, made many Paſſes at his Body with their Swords or Daggers, but not above ſeaven took place on him, by reaſon of a Quilted Waſtcoat that he wore, made of ſtiff Whale-bone; ſo that the Murderers perceiving their Weapons would not enter to kill him dead, ſaid one to another, <hi>Dam the Dog he wears Armour, let's cut his Throat,</hi> which accordingly they did giving him ſeveral diſmal Gaſhes on each ſide, but as Providence ordered it, miſs'd his Windpipe, they likewiſe ſtampt upon his Breaſt, and being afraid upon the opening of a Door hard by, left him as they thought, quite diſpatcht, one of them ſaying as he went from him, <hi>Dam me ye Dog, now pray for the Soul of Captain</hi> Evans. This <hi>Evans</hi> was that Popiſh Prieſt we mentioned before, who went by the Name of <hi>Captain,</hi> (and ſome ſay, had ſome time ſince a Commiſſion) theſe Aſſaſſinates were ſo eager to do the work, that it ſeems in the Dark they wounded one another, for Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> remembers one of them cry'd, <hi>God Dam me, ye have wounded me in the Leg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> being left in this lamentable mangled Condition, and diſintangled from the Cloak, cry'd out <hi>Murther,</hi> and was ſoon taken up and carryed home to his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at the Poſt-houſe in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> where Chyrurgions being preſently provided, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Wounds in his Throat, he was found to have received ſix more, <hi>viz.</hi> one in the Head, two in the Arm, two in the Breaſt, and one on the ſide, as alſo his Breaſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98961:3"/>lamentably bruis'd, no leſs dangerous than any of them, but yet by the Mercy of God he is in an hopeful way to be recovered, and ſurvive a <hi>Living Monument</hi> of Popiſh bloody Baſeneſs, and treacherous Cruelty.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty in Council next Morning being inform'd hereof upon Oath, there was immediately made and printed an Order of the Board, for Search and all Means to be uſed to diſcover and apprehend the Aſſaſſinates and thoſe that ſet them on, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſing 100 <hi>l.</hi> Reward to any that diſcover or take any one of them, and the like Reward and Pardon to any of them that ſhould diſcover the Reſt. At the ſame time, the Matter againſt Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi> being conſidered, though Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> was thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to attend, yet by Witneſſes ſuch Miſdemeanours were made out, that <hi>Herbert</hi> was committed to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scene</hi> 1. From this diſmal <hi>Scene,</hi> the ſecond part of <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Tragedy, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the bloody <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> their malicious revengeful Nature, and withal their <hi>Inſolence,</hi> that they dare thus attempt our Magiſtrates, and hope thereby to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighten them from their Duty. For that it was done by <hi>that Party</hi> there is no room to doubt, as well becauſe of their former <hi>Menaces,</hi> as eſpecially from the words they uſed about <hi>Evans;</hi> nay, indeed from their very <hi>Principles,</hi> which allow Murther of Hereticks, when 'tis for the Intereſt of their Catholick Cauſe. And indeed how can we expect they ſhould be merciful to our <hi>Bodies,</hi> whoſe <hi>Souls</hi> they have already doom'd to endleſs Torments, holding it impoſſible that ever one of us ſhall be ſav'd. <hi>Let me</hi> (ſaith one of their moſt famous Authors) <hi>be damn'd with</hi> Lucifer <hi>to Eternity, if ever any Proteſtant ſee the Face of God, or enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Nay, the Jeſuits publickly teach, That 'tis lawful to Aſſaſſinate any man (though a Brother-Catholick) that ſhall but give one a <hi>Box o'th' Ear,</hi> or ſhall impair ones <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp;c.</hi> much more they may <hi>butcher</hi> an Heretick that endeavours to <hi>prevent</hi> or <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> their <hi>Treaſons,</hi> or bring their Holy Fathers to Juſtice. This is ſo far from being Criminal, that 'tis Meritorious.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Again, we ought here with thankful hearts to take notice of the ſignal <hi>Series</hi> of Gracious Providence, that ever ſince the firſt <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of this Plot, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it has ſeemed to be almoſt <hi>ſtifled,</hi> and the Evidence moſt <hi>diſcouraged</hi> by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and policy of the Adverſaries; then alwayes hath infinite Wiſdom brought ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to light, or infatuated them into ſome horrid Act, which plainly has confirmed the Teſtimony of the Witneſſes, and the Wickedneſs of this bloody <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But now, As to this Reverend Father <hi>Evans,</hi> to whoſe revengeful <hi>Manes</hi> this Worthy Gentleman was to have been <hi>ſacrific'd;</hi> He was, 'tis well known, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a fair Tryal, Condemned and Executed for <hi>Treaſon:</hi> And what a Meek, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Holy, Humble Blade he was, you may partly gueſs, by his taking upon him to be of the Church-militant, with the Title of a Captain, living as a <hi>Bully,</hi> and his Mouth perpetually overflowing with Oaths and Curſes. But eſpecially you may mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his extraordinary <hi>Piety</hi> by his frequent <hi>threatnings</hi> to <hi>Piſtol</hi> this very Gentleman, as is fully proved upon Oath. Yet, after all this, that you may ſee how innocent a <hi>Lamb</hi> this ſwaggering <hi>Bell-weather</hi> is repreſented to have been at his Death, I ſhall take leave to print <hi>verbatim</hi> one of their Lying, Seducing <hi>Papers,</hi> as it was (with multitudes of the like ſtamp) printed for, or at leaſt openly ſold by <hi>Turner</hi> the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Holborn,</hi> as follows.</p>
            <div type="memoranda">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98961:3"/>
               <head>Short <hi>Memorandums</hi> upon the Deaths of Mr. <hi>Philip Evans,</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Lloyd,</hi> both Prieſts, who were Executed at <hi>Cardiff in Glamorganſhire,</hi> the 22th. day of <hi>July, 1679.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ABout Nine of the Clock in the Morning, the Under-Sheriff Mr.</hi> Charles Evans <hi>came to the Cellar in the Goal, where the Gentlemen were kept, and immediately a Smith was ſent for to take off their Irons, which were ſo hard ſet on, that the Smith was above an hour in taking off Mr.</hi> Evan<hi>'s alone, which, was not done without great pain to him; notwithſtanding which he never gave the leaſt ſign of Impatience or trouble, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the Man to go on with his work, without fear of hurting him: When they were brought out of the Cellar, they deſired to walk on Foot to the place of Execution, but were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and put both upon one Cart; their Arms Pinnioned; all the way Reading in their Books. When they Arrived at the place of Execution, they followed St.</hi> Andrews <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaying,</hi> Welcome good Croſs, <hi>and falling upon their Knees, Kiſſed the Poſt of the</hi> Gallows? <hi>and remained Praying there a good while: When they had done, they asked which was to Die first, the Sheriff anſwered, Mr.</hi> Evans; <hi>He Bowing, ſpake theſe few Words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not tell you why we are brought here to ſuffer; our Sentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is a ſufficient Witneſs, that it was not for a Plot, or any other Crime, but for being Prieſts: conſequently I do die for Religion and Conſcience ſake: I ſhall not ſpeak much of the goodneſs of my Cauſe, becauſe I think it will be heedleſs; but it is ſo good, that I would not give the happineſs of Dying for it, for all the Crowns of the World: Sure if a Man ever ſpakes truth, it muſt be at the Hour of Death, therefore <hi>I hope no Body will doubt of what I ſay;</hi> If I have or had any Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the World, which I do not know that ever I had any in my Life, I do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily forgive them, for any thing done or ſaid againſt me; and if I have offended any Body I am heartily ſorry for it, and ask them forgiveneſs; I pray God Bleſs and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the King: I beg the Prayers of all, and in particular of the <hi>Catholicks</hi> here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; <hi>That done, he Kneeled down again with ſome Friends about him, and having ſaid ſome Prayers, he took his leave of them, and went up the Ladder; upon which he ſpoke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain theſe words,</hi> Sure this is the beſt Pulpit a Man can have to Preach in, therefore I cannot forbear to tell you again, that I die for God and Religion ſake, and I think my ſelf ſo happy, that if I had never ſo many Lives, I would willingly give them all for ſo good a Cauſe; if I could Live, it would be but for a little time, though I am but young, happy am I that can purchaſe with a ſhort pain an Everlaſting Life; I do forgive all thoſe that have had any hand in my Death, Accuſation or Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I ask again forgiveneſs of every body, I give thanks to all thoſe that have been kind to me, and to you Mr. <hi>Sheriff;</hi> Adieu Mr. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> tho' for a little time, for we ſhall ſhortly meet again; pray for me all, and I ſhall return it, when it pleaſeth God that I ſhall enjoy the Beatifical Viſion, if any of you that ſee me die thus willingly for my Religion, have any good thought upon it, I ſhall think my ſelf happy; then he made a ſtop and after a little while, ſaid with a clear and cheerful voice, <hi>In ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tuas, Domine, commendo Spiritum meum; And ſo giving the ſign the Executioner turn'd him over, and the Ladder being very ſhort, it ſtirr'd with him, then Mr.</hi> Richard Jones <hi>one of the Sheriffs Bailiffs took his Legs from it, and turn'd them after his Body; all that were preſent can juſtify, that he never looked better, nor more cheerful then he did then; All this will be Teſtifyed (if need be) by Credible Perſons as well</hi> Proteſtants <hi>as</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>During the time of Mr.</hi> Evans's <hi>Execution, Mr.</hi> Lloyd <hi>stood by with us much conſtancy and cheerfulneſs as any Man could have, and before he went up the Ladder, he ſaid theſe words following more diſtinctly and heartily then ever he did in his Life, by the Report of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98961:4"/>thoſe that have known him theſe many Years.</hi> My Fellow-Sufferer has declared the Cauſe of our death, therefore I need not repeat it; and beſides I never was a good ſpeaker in my Life; I ſhall only ſay, that I die in the true <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Faith, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe words in the Creed, <hi>I Believe the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> and with thoſe three Virtues, <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity:</hi> I forgive all thoſe that have offended me; and if I have offended any body I am heartily ſorry for it, and ask them forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I beg the Prayers of all, and in particular of the <hi>Catholicks</hi> here preſent, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to bear their Croſſes patiently, and to remember that Paſſage of Holy Scripture, <hi>Happy are they that ſuffer Perſecution for Juſtice, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven: Then he went up the Ladder, and there gave thanks to all thoſe that had been kind to him, and in particular to the Sheriff, then he made a little ſtop; after which he ſaid: Mr.</hi> Carne, you have been always my Benefactor, pray for me now: <hi>Then he knocked his Breaſt three times, and ſaid in Latine;</hi> Lord have Mercy upon me a Sinner, <hi>and,</hi> Into thy hands, Lord, I recommend my Spirit: <hi>So gave the ſign and was turned over.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>Some Notes for a <hi>Comment</hi> on the foregoing Piece of <hi>Popiſh Martyrology.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. Obſerve, how Induſtrious this reſtleſs Traiterous Party is, to keep up their Damnable Cauſe; Not one of their Villanous Prieſts ſhall paſs the Gallows, but he ſhall have a Speech Forged for him, fill'd with the beſt and moſt Taking words that can be Invented, and this <hi>Printed</hi> to Proclaim him a Saint as well as a Martyr: Though in truth he liv'd a Cheat and a Ruffian, and died a <hi>Traitor</hi> and an <hi>Atheiſt.</hi> The Prieſt has done them Knight Service, what Swarms of Pamphlets do they daily throw abroad, and who almoſt Endeavours either to Suppreſs or Anſwer them, when their Compendium of the Tryals came abroad abuſing the Kings Evidence in the Groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt manner imaginable, and Endeavouring to Poiſon the People with a Disbelie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Plot. Thereby moſt inſolently giving the <hi>Lie</hi> to his Sacred Majeſty and the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Parliaments, and Vilifying not only our Courts of Judicature, but alſo two Reverend Fathers of our Church, where was then that Doughty Man of the Dead-doing Quill with his Terrible <hi>Canon,</hi> He that boaſts <hi>That where-ever his Genius tells him that his Pen may be any way uſeful to the Publick, he can no longer forbear;</hi> Was not here a fair Opportunity to Exerciſe his Talents, to Chaſtize this Uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtian,</hi> ſure here if ever his Pen might have been uſeful to Publick, yet for all this, though in part Provoked by a Reflection in the Preface to the ſaid Compendium, yet ſtill, he ſtirred not a Finger, who ſince has been Wretchedly Buſy in Scribbling <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues</hi> and <hi>Back-Stroke Complements</hi> againſt <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oats;</hi> But alas! The Gentleman was then perhaps at his Old Profeſſion of the <hi>Merry Crowd,</hi> or the Studying the Myſtery of <hi>Monkey-making,</hi> which he has ſince ſo Laudably Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Note, That the ſubtle Contriver would fain Inſinuate <hi>Tortures</hi> or <hi>Harſh Uſage,</hi> by that Fooliſh Lie. <hi>That the Smith was above an hour in taking off of</hi> Evans<hi>'s Irons;</hi> As if it were unuſual to keep Traitors for their ſafe Cuſtody in <hi>Fetters,</hi> but tell us pray how you uſe poor <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> when they have caught them in their <hi>Barbarous Inquiſition?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>He kiſſed the Poſt of the Gallows.</hi> Is not the Gibbet, think you, <hi>ſanctified</hi> by this holy Martyr's Kiſs? we ſhall have it <hi>ſtollen away</hi> ſhortly, and ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> to make <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> of.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The dying Father begins his <hi>Harangue</hi> with a <hi>Lie;</hi> That <hi>their Sentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſhews that they died for no other Crime, but for being Prieſts;</hi> for they were Condemned for being <hi>Traytors;</hi> and that moſt juſtly, for <hi>being the Kings natural born Subjects, they had gone beyond the Seas in defiance to his Laws, and there ſworn Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to a Foreign Enemy; and again, in Contempt of Law, were returned, and did dayly juſtifie, and by Preaching and Practiſe maintain the Authority and Juriſdiction of ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98961:4"/>Foreign Uſurpers within his Majesties Dominions,</hi> which is in effect an <hi>Invading</hi> of his Kingdoms and Sovereignty, and <hi>Depoſing</hi> and <hi>Overthrowing</hi> of his Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And who can doubt whether doing all this be Treaſon? yet ſtill theſe Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains make an <hi>Outcry</hi> that they die for their <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. The truth is, we may juſtly ſay, that not only Popiſh Prieſts, but every <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (that is the King's Natural born Subject) is a <hi>Traytor;</hi> for owning himſelf to be of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he muſt hold that the Pope has right to ſome ſpiritual Juriſdiction within our Kings Dominions; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o affirm, is to take away part of his Imperial Crown; and as 'tis againſt all Truth, ſo by the Laws of this Realm it is <hi>Treaſon.</hi> Yet this is the Party which boaſts ſo much of their Loyalty, when in truth, they are every one of them in their Principles <hi>Dogmatical Traytors;</hi> nor will they ever fail to put the ſame into Act and Practice longer than only whilſt they want ſtrength or opportunity.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He hopes <hi>No body will doubt of what he ſays.</hi> But the Scripture tells us, <hi>The Hope of the Hypocrite ſhall periſh.</hi> We are too well acquainted with their dying Lies, to believe them. We remember Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> who took it upon his Death, that he was never in <hi>London</hi> between the 5th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and the 14th. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> which is proved a notorious Lie, not only by Mr. <hi>Jenniſon</hi> and others, but alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own hand, in his Pocket-Book ſince found.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He ſays, <hi>He does not know that ever he had any Enemies in his Life.</hi> Sure this Father was the <hi>Phenix</hi> of the Age! Not ſo much as one Enemy Man, and yet a Captain! Surely, ſurely, he had learned to be an Enemy, if not to have one; for undoubtedly his threatning treacherouſly to Piſtol Mr. <hi>Arnold,</hi> was no ſign of Friendſhip.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Whereas he ſays, <hi>The Gallows is the beſt Pulpit that can be had to Preach in:</hi> I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily agree with him, that it is for ſuch Divines as himſelf. For what his Divinity was, appears by the next words; He is for purchaſing <hi>Everlaſting Life</hi> with an <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> his own ſmall pain he reckons a ſufficient price for it, and ſo never ſpeaks a word of the <hi>merits</hi> or <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. When he deſires the people <hi>to pray for him,</hi> he is very Givil in promiſing <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Complement</hi> and pray for them again, when he ſhould have blundered through Purgatory: This looks like an ambitious Rogues trick, to beſpeak beforehand the veneration and prayers of his filly tribe: that they may put him in mind of his promiſe, and to the end he (forſooth) may pray again for them.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. We do not hear one word of an <hi>Ave Maria</hi> here; What, had theſe Fellows forgot their good Lady, that uſed to engroſe almoſt all their Lip-Devotions? what ſhould the meaning that neither her help, nor any other Saints is invok'd? Ile tell you, we may juſtly believe this pretty ſmall Speech was hatch'd here by ſome idle Father in Town, and publiſh'd only to amuſe the world; and becauſe they thought it would go down better with Proteſtants, and move them more to compaſſion and better eſteem for Popery if they found no ſuch vain Addreſſes in it; therefore they were left out: for theſe ſubtil Sophiſters contrive every thing for the beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which yet notwithſtanding all their Craft and Diligence, their private Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, and baſe Treacheries, and barbarous Cruelties, God moſt aſſuredly will <hi>blaſt</hi> and confound all thoſe that are Actors in, or Connivers at, and Abettors of the traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Helliſh Deſign of re-eſtabliſhing <hi>Popery</hi> in theſe Nations: And therefore let not Proteſtants deſpond, but unanimouſly and chearfully in their ſeveral ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by all lawful ways oppoſe their Machinations; nor let any Magiſtrate be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to do his Duty by putting the Laws vigorouſly in execution againſt theſe perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Vermin; dread not their treacherous Daggers, nor their ſuborn'd Witneſſes, nor their potent Friends; for without the ſpecial permiſſion of your God, they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98961:5"/>ſhall never be able to touch one hair of your Head; or ſuppoſe they ſhall be allowed to effect ſome Bvtchery, can any man do more nobly than <hi>pro Aris &amp; Foris,</hi> for his Religion and his Countrey, and whenever theſe inhumane Ruffians thus draw their Daggers, do they not always <hi>ſtab</hi> their own <hi>Cauſe</hi> in a vital part. Thoſe Magiſtrates that in this Critical Juncture ſhall gallantly appear to deſtroy this <hi>Hydra</hi> of Popery, and to ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and the <hi>Government</hi> from ſubverſion, ſhall be bleſſed by Heaven, and applauded on Earth to ſucceeding generations; but thoſe that ſhall by <hi>Villany</hi> or <hi>Cowardice</hi> go about to betray the Life of their King, and our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> into the hands of <hi>Bloody Papiſts,</hi> divine Vengeance ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them, and their Names ſhall be cloathed with everlaſting Infamy, and the Curſe of <hi>Slavery</hi> ſhall deſcend upon their Poſterity.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
